Take a look at this drawing.
ألقوا نظرةً على هذا الرسم.
Can you tell what it is?
هل يمكنكم أن تخبروني ما هذا؟
I'm a molecular biologist by training,
أنا أخصائية أحياء جزيئية بالتدريب
and I've seen a lot of these kinds of drawings.
وقد رأيت كثيرًا من أنواع هذه الرسوم.
They're usually referred to as a model figure,
عادةً ما يشار إليها كنموذج إيضاح،
a drawing that shows how we think
رسم يوضح تصورنا
a cellular or molecular process occurs.
لحدوث عملية خلوية أو جزيئية.
This particular drawing is of a process
هذا الشكل تحديدًا لعملية
called clathrin-mediated endocytosis.
تسمي الالتقام الخلوي بواسطة الكلاذرين.
It's a process by which a molecule can get
العملية التي من خلالها يستطيع جزيء
from the outside of the cell to the inside
من خارج الخلية الانتقال إلى داخلها
by getting captured in a bubble or a vesicle
عبر الاستحواذ عليه في فقاعة أو حويصلة
that then gets internalized by the cell.
ثم تقوم الخلية بإدخاله.
There's a problem with this drawing, though,
توجد مشكلة في هذا الرسم، بالرغم من أنه،
and it's mainly in what it doesn't show.
وفي الغالب تكون أساسًا فيما لا يظهر.
From lots of experiments,
من تجارب عديدة،
from lots of different scientists,
ومن علماء مختلفين كثر،
we know a lot about what these molecules look like,
نعرف كثيرًا عما تبدوا عليه هذه الجزيئات،
how they move around in the cell,
وكيف تتحرك في الخلية،
and that this is all taking place
وأن هذا كله يأخذ حيزا
in an incredibly dynamic environment.
بشكل لا يصدق في بيئة ديناميكية.
So in collaboration with a clathrin expert Tomas Kirchhausen,
بالتعاون مع خبير الكلاذرين توماس كيركاوزون
we decided to create a new kind of model figure
قررنا أن ننشئ شكلًا إيضاحيًا من نوع جديد
that showed all of that.
يوضح كل ذلك.
So we start outside of the cell.
نحن نبدأ خارج الخلية.
Now we're looking inside.
الآن ننظر في الداخل.
Clathrin are these three-legged molecules
الكلاذرين هي تلك الجزيئات الثلاثية الأرجل
that can self-assemble into soccer-ball-like shapes.
تستطيع أن تتجمع تلقائيًا في أشكال تشبه كرة القدم.
Through connections with a membrane,
من خلال اتصال الأغشية سويًا،
clathrin is able to deform the membrane
الكلاذرين قادرًا على تفكيك الغشاء
and form this sort of a cup
وتشكيل هذا النوع من الكؤوس
that forms this sort of a bubble, or a vesicle,
التي تشكل هذا النوع من الفقاعات، أو الحويصلات،
that's now capturing some of the proteins
التي تستحوذ الآن على بعض البروتين
that were outside of the cell.
التي كانت خارج الخلية.
Proteins are coming in now that basically pinch off this vesicle,
البروتينات التي تدخل الآن أساسًا أخذت من هذه الحويصلة،
making it separate from the rest of the membrane,
مما يجعلها تنفصل عن باقي الغشاء،
and now clathrin is basically done with its job,
والآن أتم الكلاذرين وظيفته تمامًا،
and so proteins are coming in now —
ثم تدخل البروتينات الآن ــ
we've covered them yellow and orange —
قمنا بتغطيتها بالأصفر والبرتقالي ـــ
that are responsible for taking apart this clathrin cage.
والتي هي مسئولة عن أخذ قفص الكلاذرين هذا بعيدًا.
And so all of these proteins can get basically recycled
وكل تلك البروتينات يمكن إعادة تدويرها
and used all over again.
واستخدامها جميعًا مرة أخرى.
These processes are too small to be seen directly,
تلك العمليات صغيرة جدًا لترى مباشرةً
even with the best microscopes,
حتى بواسطة أفضل مجهر ضوئي،
so animations like this provide a really powerful way
لذلك رسوم متحركة مثل هذه توفر وسيلة قوية حقًا
of visualizing a hypothesis.
لتصور فرضي.
Here's another illustration,
هنا رسم إيضاحي آخر،
and this is a drawing of how a researcher might think
وهذا رسم عن كيف يمكن أن يتصور الباحثون
that the HIV virus gets into and out of cells.
دخول فيروس الإيدز لداخل الخلية والخروج منها.
And again, this is a vast oversimplification
ومرة أخرى، هذا تبسيط مفرط
and doesn't begin to show
ولا يبدأ في إظهار
what we actually know about these processes.
ما نعرف فعليًا عن هذه العمليات.
You might be surprised to know
قد تتفاجؤون لمعرفة
that these simple drawings are the only way
أن تلك الرسوم البسيطة هي الوسيلة الوحيدة
that most biologists visualize their molecular hypotheses.
التي يتصور بها معظم البيولوجيون افتراضاتهم الجزيئية.
Why?
لماذا؟
Because creating movies of processes
لأن إنشاء أفلام للعمليات
as we think they actually occur is really hard.
كما نتصور حدوثها فعليًا صعب حقًا.
I spent months in Hollywood learning 3D animation software,
قضيت شهورًا في هوليوود أتعلم برامج الرسوم المتحركة ثلاثية الأبعاد،
and I spend months on each animation,
وقضيت شهور في كل رسم متحرك،
and that's just time that most researchers can't afford.
وذلك الوقت فقط معظم الباحثون لا يستطيعون تحمله.
The payoffs can be huge, though.
الفائدة يمكن أن تكون ضخمة، رغم ذلك.
Molecular animations are unparalleled
الرسوم المتحركة الجزيئية لا مثيل لها
in their ability to convey a great deal of information
في قدرتها على نقل قدر كبير من المعلومات
to broad audiences with extreme accuracy.
لجماهير عريضة بدقة قصوى.
And I'm working on a new project now
وأنا الآن أعمل على مشروع جديد
called "The Science of HIV"
يسمى "علم فيروس الإيدز"
where I'll be animating the entire life cycle
حيث سوف أقوم بعمل رسوم متحركة لدورة
of the HIV virus as accurately as possible
حياة الفيروس كاملةً بأكبر دقة ممكنة
and all in molecular detail.
وبكل التفاصيل الجزيئية.
The animation will feature data
الرسوم المتحركة سوف تبرز بيانات
from thousands of researchers collected over decades,
من آلاف الباحثين تم جمعها عبر عقود،
data on what this virus looks like,
بيانات عما يبدو عليه هذا الفيروس،
how it's able to infect cells in our body,
كيفية قدرته على إصابة خلايا أجسامنا.
and how therapeutics are helping to combat infection.
وكيف يساعد العلاج في مكافحة العدوى.
Over the years, I found that animations
عبر أعوام، وجدت أن الرسوم المتحركة
aren't just useful for communicating an idea,
ليست مفيدة فقط في توصيل فكرة،
but they're also really useful
لكنها حقًا مفيدةً أيضًا
for exploring a hypothesis.
لاستكشاف فرضيةً.
Biologists for the most part are still using a paper and pencil
النسبة الأكبر من البيولوجيين لا يزالون يستخدمون
to visualize the processes they study,
الورقة وقلم الرصاص لتصور العمليات التي
and with the data we have now, that's just not good enough anymore.
يدرسونها، وبالبيانات التي نمتلكها الآن، هذا لم يعد جيد بما يكفي.
The process of creating an animation
عملية إنشاء رسم متحرك
can act as a catalyst that allows researchers
يمكن أن تقوم بدور الحافز الذي يسمح للباحثين
to crystalize and refine their own ideas.
ببلورة وتحسين أفكارهم الخاصة.
One researcher I worked with
واحدة من الباحثين الذين عملت معهم
who works on the molecular mechanisms
تعمل على الآليات الجزيئية
of neurodegenerative diseases
للأمراض العصبية
came up with experiments that were related
جاءت بتجارب مرتبطة
directly to the animation that she and I worked on together,
مباشرةً مع رسم متحرك عملنا أنا وهي عليه سويًا،
and in this way, animation can feed back into the research process.
وبهذه الطريقة، يمكن للرسم المتحرك تغذية العملية البحثية.
I believe that animation can change biology.
أنا مؤمنة بأن الرسوم المتحركة يمكنها تغيير علم الأحياء.
It can change the way that we communicate with one another,
يمكنها تغيير الطريقة التي نتواصل بها مع بعضنا البعض،
how we explore our data
كيف نستكشف بياناتنا
and how we teach our students.
وكيف نعلم طلابنا.
But for that change to happen,
لكن ليحدث ذلك التغيير
we need more researchers creating animations,
نحن بحاجة لبحاثين أكثر ينشئون رسومًا متحركةً،
and toward that end, I brought together a team
وباتجاه هذه النهاية، أحضرت فريق من
of biologists, animators and programmers
البيولوجيين، ورسامي الرسوم المتحركة، والمبرمجين
to create a new, free, open-source software —
لإنشاء برنامج جديد ومجاني، ومفتوح المصدر ـــ
we call it Molecular Flipbook —
يمكننا تسميته الكتيب الجزيئي ـــ
that's created just for biologists
أنشئ هذا فقط للبيولوجيين
just to create molecular animations.
فقط لإنشاء رسومًا متحركةً جزيئيةً.
From our testing, we've found that it only takes 15 minutes
من تجربتنا، قد وجدنا ذلك يأخذ فقط 15 دقيقة
for a biologist who has never touched animation software before
للبيولوجي الذي لم يتعامل أبدًا مع برنامج رسوم متحركة من قبل
to create her first molecular animation
لإنشاء رسمه المتحرك الجزيئي الأول
of her own hypothesis.
لافتراضه الخاص.
We're also building an online database
وأيضًا نبني قاعدة بيانات على الإنترنت
where anyone can view, download and contribute
حيث أي شخص يمكنه مشاهدة، وتحميل ومشاركة
their own animations.
رسومهم المتحركة الخاصة.
We're really excited to announce
نحن متشوقون حقًا للإعلان
that the beta version of the molecular animation
أن الإصدار التجريبي لبرنامج الرسم المتحرك الجزيئي
software toolkit will be available for download today.
سوف يكون متاحًا للتحميل اليوم.
We are really excited to see what biologists will create with it
نحن متشوقون حقًا لرؤية ما سينشئ البيولوجيون به
and what new insights they're able to gain
وما الرؤى الجديدة التي بمقدورهم كسبها
from finally being able to animate
من قدرتهم النهائية على تحريك
their own model figures.
أشكالهم التوضيحية الخاصة.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)